<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">
	<a name="Description"/>
	<h3>Description</h3>
	<p>Use this operation to retrieve variants with precise endpoints from a specified genomic region for a specified patient. If the range in question has been studied, the operation returns variants overlapping the region. If the patient or the specified region has not been studied, the operation returns a 404 error.
</p>
	<a name="INParameters"/>
	<h3>IN Parameters</h3>
	<ul>
		<li>Region of interest is specified as a 0-based interval range of integers. Variants that overlap the range (variants 1-5 in the picture) would be returned, as would a point mutation at position x, but not a point mutation at position y. (Note that an insertion that starts before x, regardless of length, would not overlap x..y, and would therefore not be returned).</li>
		<li>Genomic reference sequence is a valid NCBI chromosome-level ('NC_') <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/assembly/GCF_000001405.13/">build 37</a> or <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/assembly/GCF_000001405.26/">build 38</a> identifier, or a valid mitochondrion identifier (NC_012920.1, NC_001807.4).</li>
	</ul>
	<img src="find-variants-fig1.png" alt="region of interest"/>
	<a name="OUTParameters"> </a>
	<h3>OUT Parameters</h3>	
	<ul>
		<li>Response shall include 1..1 observation (RegionStudied), 0..* observation (Variant), 0..* observation (SequencePhaseRelationship).</li> 
		<li>Variants must be represented using a combination of all of these components: genomic-ref-seq; ref-allele; alt-allele; coordinate-system (valued with '0-based interval counting'); exact-start-end. Additional representations can optionally be included.</li>
		<li>Implicit in this service is that variants in the requested range, regardless of how they are formatted or stored in a server, are returned. See 'Variant normalization' section below for guidance on variant normalization.</li>
		<li>An implementation only need respond with variants based on the requested build (the build implicit in the reference sequence). See 'Variant liftover' section below for additional comments of normalizing across different builds.</li>
		<li>If the region hasn't been studied, return a 404 response code. </li>
	</ul>
</div>