<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">
  <p>
    The <b>Described Variant</b> has a large number of properties.  However these properties fall into groups, where each group of properties has a purpose (and in some cases represents information that typically appears together).  The groups of properties are described below:
  </p>
  
  <a name="location"> </a>
  <h3>Variant Location properties</h3>
  <p>
    These are properties that help to describe <i>where</i> a particular variation occurs. Considering the reference sequence <code>genomic-ref-seq:48013-7</code> and coordinate system <code>coordinate-system:TBD</code>, the component <code>allele-start-end:81254-5</code> can denote the first and last genomic positions in the reference that correspond to changes. If the observation points to a <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}molecularsequence.html">MolecularSequence</a> resource as a reference sequence, then that resource will carry this information under <code>variant.start</code> and <code>variant.end</code>.
  </p>
  <p>
  	Additionally, if the exact start and end positions are unknown, <code>outer-start-end:81301-4</code> and <code>inner-start-end:81302-2</code> can be used to deliver the boundaries of where the variant begins and ends. 
  </p>
  <a name="Variant Change"> </a>
  <h3>Variant Change Components</h3>
  <p>
    The components <code>dna-chg:48004-6</code> and <code>dna-chg-type:48019-4</code> are used to deliver the Human Genome Variation Society (HGVS) nomenclature for the observed DNA marker and codify the type of change observed. If the described variant is structural, <code>genomic-dna-chg:81290-9</code> is used instead of <code>dna-chg:48004-6</code>. If a simple variant is observed, the component <code>variation-code:81252-9</code> is used to report the variant's unique identifier. Alternatively, <code>dbSNP-id:81255-2</code> can be used to represent the change, and/or the components <code>ref-allele:69547-8</code> and <code>alt-allele:69551-0</code> can directly relay the variation from the observed sequence. 
  </p>
  <p>
    Lastly, <code>genomic-source-class:48002-0</code> can describe the genomic class of the specimen being analyzed, whether it is from inherited genome, cancer genome, or fetal genome.
  </p>
  <a name="Allelic State"> </a>
  <h3>Allelic State Components</h3>
  <p>
    The components <code>allelic-frequency:81258-6</code>, <code>allelic-read-depth:82121-5</code>, and <code>allelic-state:53034-5</code> indicate infomartion about a particular allele. Namely, they communicate the relative frequency of the allele in the population, the number of reads that identified it, and the observed level of occurence within a set of chromosomes, respectively.
  </p>
  <a name="Amino Acid Change"> </a>
  <h3>Amino Acid Change Components</h3>
  <p>
    The components <code>amino-acid-chg:48005-3</code> and <code>amino-acid-chg-type:48006-1</code> are used when communicating a variant in an amino acid sequence. Human Genome Variation Society (HGVS) nomenclature is used.
  </p>

  <a name="Genomic Location"> </a>
  <h3>Genomic Location Components</h3>
  <p>
    The components <code>gene-studied:48018-6</code> and <code>cytogenetic-location:48001-2</code> are used to describe the cytogenetic chromosome location and the HUGO Gene Nomenclature Committee (HGNC) identifier for a gene studied.
  </p>  
</div>
