<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">
	<a name="Description"/>
	<h3>Description</h3>
	<p>Retrieve metadata about sequencing studies performed on a subject.</p>
	
	 <blockquote class="stu-note">
    <p>
      The Clinical Genomics committee is reviewing <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-35864">Jira 35864: Add study-level metadata capabilities into the FHIR Genomics IG</a>. It is expected that the response of this operation will be revised in the future, to align with the Jira resolution.
    </p>
  </blockquote>
	
	<p><b>Test Id</b> and <b>test date</b> are always returned. Additional metadata is server dependent, and specific implementations can indicate their capabilities using a <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/capabilitystatement.html">FHIR Capability Statement</a>. Frequently useful metadata includes <b>Specimen Id</b> and <b>Genomic build</b> (reference sequence assembly upon which variants were called, e.g. 'GRCh37', 'GRCh38'). Additionally, it can be useful to indicate the <b>DNA change types</b> or types of variants detectable by the test (e.g. 'SNV', 'InDel', 'CNV'). Servers can choose to return additional metadata.</p>
	
	<p>As described in <a href="operations.html#query-filters">general guidance</a>, metadata can be used to filter the results of other operations.</p> 
	
	<p>In some scenarios, users need to know whether or not a particular genomic region was studied by a given test (<b>studied region</b>), and whether or not there are uncallable subregions within regions studied (<b>uncallable regions</b>). Genomic sequencing tests are designed to study specific portions of a person's genome. For instance, whole genome sequencing (WGS) tests are designed to study the entire genome; whole exome sequencing (WES) tests are designed to study protein-coding exons; targeted sequencing tests are designed to only study selected regions of the genome. In many cases, while a particular region was targeted to be studied by a given test, a portion of the region might be untestable, due to patient-specific factors, reagent-specific factors, etc. Whereas labs report variants found to be present, labs cannot enumerate every variant found to be absent - when you consider that a person has 4 billion base pairs, 99% of which are the same as a reference sequence, you can imagine how big a report would need to be to enumerate every variant found to be absent! Rather, absence of a variant at a particular position can potentially be inferred by knowing the region studied, and whether or not there were uncallable subregions within the studied region.</p>
<p>	Users can request this level of detail by including the <b>ranges</b> parameter, in which case each returned test will include 
<b>intersecting</b> studied and uncallable regions. Studied and uncallable regions can be voluminous - data can be curtailed by specifying appropriately narrow ranges. Range data is returned as a list of non-overlapping regions, each in zero-based RefSeq:Integer-range format (e.g. "['NC_000007.14:55173910-55174053', 'NC_000007.14:55174711-55174830', 'NC_000007.14:55181282-55181488']"). </p>

</div>


