<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">
  <blockquote class="stu-note">
    <p>
    The content in this section may be significantly revised prior to the next ballot after initial use and feedback.
    </p>
	  
  </blockquote>
  <p>
		The Genomic Implication profile is an abstract for the Theraputic and Diagnostic implications. Implications are relevant information which is derieved from the presence of a haplotype, genotype, variant or other observed genetic change.
	This portion of the implementation guide relies on the content in the <a href="general.html">General Genomic Reporting</a> and <a href="sequencing.html">Variant Reporting</a> portions of this implementation guide.  
  </p>

	<a name="Differentiating AND vs OR"> </a>
	<h3>Differentiating AND vs OR</h3>
	<p>
		There are several cases where it is necessary to differentiate 'AND' conditions (e.g. both drug X AND drug Y, in combination, are indicated in the presence of a variant) vs. 'OR' conditions (e.g. either drug X OR drug Y are indicated in the presence of a variant).
		This situation is not unique to genomic implications, and arises elsewhere within FHIR (e.g. <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/search.html#combining">FHIR Search</a>) and outside of FHIR (e.g. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar/docs/api_http/">Clinvar submission API</a> condition set). To be consistent with other precedents:
	</p>
	<p>
		Where Diagnostic and Therapeutic implications have fields with cardinality >1, the inclusion of multiple values within a field shall indicate an 'AND' condition. An 'OR' condition is represented by multiple observation instances.

	</p>
	<p>
		Implication fields affected by this guidance include:
	</p>
	<p>
		<a href="StructureDefinition-therapeutic-implication.html">Therapeutic implications</a>:
	</p>
	<p>
		derivedFrom, evidence-level, phenotypic-treatment-context, medication-assessed, therapy-assessed, predicted-therapeutic-implication.
	</p>
	<p>
		<a href="StructureDefinition-diagnostic-implication.html">Diagnostic implications</a>:
	</p>
	<p>
		derivedFrom, evidence-level, predicted-phenotype, functional-effect, genomics-report-risk.
	</p>
	<p>
		As an example, assume Variant X is pathogenic for Disease Y AND Disease Z in combination. This would be a single diagnostic implication, where predicted-phenotype is a list containing both Disease Y and Disease Z. If on the other hand, Variant X might be pathogenic for Disease Y alone, or Disease Z alone, this would be two diagnostic implications, one containing a predicted-phenotype of Disease Y, and the other containing a predicted-phenotype of Disease Z.

	</p>
</div>