<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">

	<a name="Scope and Usage"> </a>
	<h3>Scope and Usage</h3>

  <p>
    The primary focus of genomic testing is making Genomic Findings. These are the fine and/or coarse-grained descriptions of a specimen's genomic characteristics. This profile is the base profile for all other finding profiles, defining a set of constraints that are applicable across all findings.
  </p>
  <img src="general-genomic-findings.png" alt="Class diagram showing relationship of genomic findings as well as genotypes, haplotypes, variants and sequences."  width="522" height="325"/>
  <p>
    <b>Genomic Findings</b>
  </p>
  <p>
    <a href="StructureDefinition-finding.html">Genomic Finding</a>,
    <a href="StructureDefinition-genotype.html">Genotype</a>,
    <a href="StructureDefinition-haplotype.html">Haplotype</a>,
    <a href="StructureDefinition-variant.html"> Variant</a> (or see <a href="sequencing.html">Variant Reporting</a>),
    <a href="StructureDefinition-sequence-phase-relationship.html">Sequence Phase Relationship</a>
  </p>

	<a name="Types of Findings"> </a>
	<h4>Types of Findings</h4>

  <ul>
    <li><a href="StructureDefinition-genotype.html">Genotypes</a> describe combinations of genomic variations that together are associated with a particular phenotype - i.e., a specific physical, behavioral, or risk-associated difference associated with the organism whose specimen was tested.</li>
    <li><a href="StructureDefinition-haplotype.html">Haplotypes</a> describe a set of genomic variations that appear on a single strand of DNA - and which are therefore typically inherited together</li>
    <li>Variants are specific differences or combinations of differences between parts of one or more specimen sequences and the equivalent portions of the reference sequence(s) for that organism. The <a href="sequencing.html">Variant Reporting</a> section deals with all types of variants detected by formal sequencing, including simple/discrete variants, structural variants and complex variants detected by direct sequencing, shotgun-based sequencing, and array-based testing for specific variants.</li>
    <li><a href="StructureDefinition-sequence-phase-relationship.html">Sequence Phase Relationships</a> describe the CIS or TRANS relationship of findings.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    These categories of observations have relationships. Haplotypes can be identified based on the presence of variants. Genotypes can be identified based on the presence of haplotypes and/or variants. All three can be expressed as a combination of one or more sequences.
  </p>

	<a name="Common Elements"> </a>
	<h4>Common Elements</h4>

 <p>
  <ul>
    <li><code>gene-studied (component)</code> represents the gene(s) for the finding.</li>
    <li><code>cytogenetic-location (component)</code> represents the chromosome, arm, and band (can be multiple) for the finding</li>
    <li><code>reference-sequence-assembly (component)</code> represents reference sequence used when determining this finding</li>
  </ul>
</p>

</div>