<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">

  <p>
    Genotype describes combinations of genomic variations that together are associated with a particular phenotype - i.e., a specific physical, behavioral, or risk-associated difference associated with the organism whose specimen was tested. Genotype is used to convey corresponding <a href="StructureDefinition-haplotype.html">haplotypes</a> or <a href="StructureDefinition-variant.html">variations</a> at a particular locus. Many genotypes are expressed as simple strings, and can be conveyed in <code>valueCodeableConcept.text</code>. In some cases, genotypes are sufficiently standardized to be conveyed as codes in <code>valueCodeableConcept.code</code>.
    <ul>
      <li><code>TPMT *1/*3A</code> represents the TPMT *1 haplotype (or 'star allele') on one chromosome and the TPMT *3A haplotype on the homologous chromosome</li>
      <li><code>A/C</code> represents a heterozygous "A" and a heterozygous "C" at SNP rs1142345. </li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    For HLA, KIR, and other genes in the immunogenomics domain, the National Marrow Donor Program (NMDP) led a community effort to define the Genotype List String (GL String) grammar, described <a href="https://glstring.org">here</a>. Notably, the GL String uses '+' as a delimiter between alleles in a genotype. It also has delimiters for ambiguous genotypes, allele lists, and haplotypes.
  </p>
  <p>
    For Pharmacogenomics, we define here a simple grammar of [HGNC gene symbol followed by white space followed by a slash ('/') delimited list of haplotype codes], where the codeSystem is set to the codeSystem of the haplotypes (e.g., PharmVar).
  </p>
  <p>
    Here are some examples that are standardized, note that there are some other examples which still lack standardization today.
    <ul>
      <li>Text only<br/>
        <div class="example"><pre class="json">
{
  "valueCodeableConcept": {
    "text": "A/C at SNP rs1142345"
  }
}
        </pre></div>
      </li>
      <li>Coded HLA<br/>
        <div class="example"><pre class="json">
{
  "valueCodeableConcept": {
    "coding": [{
      "system": "http://glstring.org",
      "version": "1.0",
      "code": "#hla#3.23#HLA-A*01:01:01:01/HLA-A*01:02+HLA-A*24:02:01:01"
    }]
  }
}
        </pre></div>
      </li>
      <li>Coded PGx<br/>
        <div class="example"><pre class="json">
{
  "valueCodeableConcept": {
    "coding": [{
      "system": "http://www.pharmvar.org",
      "code": "PV00044",
      "display": "CYP2C9*2.001"
    }]
  }
}
        </pre></div>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    For both genotypes and haplotypes, reporting the structured variant data is optional. However, it is always recommended when possible. For example, sending PGX star-alleles without variant-level information is not best practice as it is both potentially ambiguous and can preclude future utility of the report.
  </p>
</div>
