<!-- somatics.xml {% comment %}
*****************************************************************************************
*                            WARNING: DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE                             *
*                                                                                       *
* This file is generated by SUSHI. Any edits you make to this file will be overwritten. *
*                                                                                       *
* To change the contents of this file, edit the original source file at:                *
* genomics-reporting/input/pages/somatics.xml                                           *
*****************************************************************************************
{% endcomment %} -->
<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">
  <p>
    This section deals with reporting observations related to cancer genomics. This includes reporting variants found in a tumor specimen, germ-line variants with known links to somatic events such as increasing risk for developing particular cancers, molecular biomarker observations that affect cancer care, and more. Beyond reporting variants and biomarkers, we also provide "implication" profiles to communicate observed links between variants and relevant knowledge bases such as professional guidelines and publications, for diagnostic and therapeutic implications, for predicted oncogenicity, etc. This sort of reporting is particularly prominent when dealing with cancer-related specimens, but can also include transplanted tissue and other forms of mosaicism. </p>

  <p>
    Some of the profiles used for somatic reporting make reference to medications and other therapies. Because this implementation guide is intended for international use, it does not mandate the use of any particular code systems for medications or other therapies.  Implementations should use the code systems most typically used in their jurisdictions or that are mandated by national FHIR profiles.
  </p>

  <a name="general"> </a>
  <h3>General guidance</h3>
  <p>
    While not specifically profiled in this version of the IG, some additional constraints will typically apply to somatic reporting.  Patient will typically be mandatory as somatics is not relevant for environmental samples.  Body structure will often be identified to allow associating results with specific tumors or lesions - even if multiple samples are drawn over time.
  </p>

  <a name="implications"> </a>
  <h3>Implications</h3>
  <img src="figureonSomaticPage.png" alt="Diagram showing implication profiles" width="670" height="362"/>
  <p>
    <b>Figure 1: Implication Profiles</b>
  </p>
  <p>
    (Profile links:
    <a href="StructureDefinition-implication.html">Genomic Implication (abstract)</a>,
    <a href="StructureDefinition-diagnostic-implication.html">Diagnostic Implication</a>,
    <a href="StructureDefinition-therapeutic-implication.html">Therapeutic Implication</a>,
	<a href="StructureDefinition-molecular-consequence.html"> Molecular Consequence</a>)
  </p>
  <p>
    This implementation guide defines implication profiles that can be used for reporting somatic use cases. They carry a collection of components that provide context for the implication, which can be captured in <code>Observation.note</code> as the issuing lab desires.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>Diagnostic Implication</b> indicates an association between the identified variant (linked via <code>Observation.derivedFrom</code>) and a particular type of cancer in the <code>predicted-phenotype</code> component. The <code>evidence-level</code> and <code>clinical-significance</code> components can convey the evidence-based categorization of the variant for the given cancer type per the AMP/ASCO/CAP guidelines, FDA Levels, etc.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>Therapeutic Implication</b> indicates an association between the identified variant (linked via <code>Observation.derivedFrom</code>) and the efficacy of a particular medication or therapy for the specified cancer. Because this implementation guide is intended for international use, it does not mandate the use of any particular code systems for medications, therapies, or cancer descriptions. Implementations should use the code systems most typically used in their jurisdictions or that are mandated by national FHIR profiles.

  </p>
  <p>
    <b>Molecular Consequence</b> indicates the calculated or observed effect of a DNA variant (linked via <code>Observation.derivedFrom</code>) on its downstream transcript and, if applicable, ensuing protein sequence.</p>


  <a name="examples"> </a>
  <h3>Somatic-specific example instances</h3>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="Bundle-bundle-oncologyexamples-r4.html">Full transaction bundle</a> containing a Genomics DiagnosticReport referencing, Patient, Practicioner, Specimen, with Tumor Mutational Burden and MSI Status Observations, Variant Observations for JAK2/KDR/ERBB4 SNV analyses, and 4 derived Therapeutic Implication Observations.
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="Bundle-bundle-oncology-report-example.html">Multiple Oncology Variant Report Example</a> Oncology Example Report with 12 reported somatic variants
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="Bundle-bundle-oncology-diagnostic.html">Melanoma implication</a> Small example report with 1 reported variant and diagnostic implication.

    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="somaticExample.html">Detailed Somatic Example</a> is a detailed somatic example that includes a mock report (in PDF) with a mapping to the underlying FHIR instances. The report is deliberately comprehensive, showing a wide range of findings and implications, along with report metadata.

    </li>
  </ul>

</div>
